so let's look at a problem
regarding isotopic abundance and atomic
mass. the question says the abundances of
the following silicon isotopes are as
follows: silicon 28 is ninety two point
two three percent, silicon 29 is four
point six seven percent, and silicon 30
is 3.10% so that means out of all the
silicon atoms in the universe ninety two
point two three percent of them weigh
twenty-eight atomic mass units, four
point six seven percent of them weigh
twenty nine atomic mass units, and three
point one zero percent of them weigh
thirty atomic mass units. so the question
is what is the average atomic mass of
silicon. so if this is confusing go and
check out my tutorial on nuclides
symbols, we want to understand atomic
mass we want to understand atomic number
and mass number and we want to
understand what isotopes are, so if you
are unclear go ahead and check out that
tutorial first, if everything makes sense give this a shot.
so here are the
relevant values, now what are we going to
do with them? as it turns out to get the
average atomic mass all we need to do is
multiply the mass number of each isotope
by its abundance, so let's do that now.
first we have silicon 28 so let's put 28
times zero point nine two two three
that is 92 point two three percent of
one, or a whole. to that we will add 29
for the mass number of silicon 29 and
multiply that by zero point zero four
six seven, that is four point six seven
percent of one or a whole, which
represents the atomic mass
of silicon. and lastly we have 30 for the
mass number of silicon 30 and we will
multiply that by zero point zero three
one zero, which is three point one zero
percent of one. and now all we need to do
is add these up. let's also be clear that
our answer should have three sig figs
because these values in the parentheses
have four sig figs, three sig figs, and
three sig figs respectively, so that will
limit our answer to three sig figs. and
if we plug all of that into a calculator
we do get 28 point one and that is the
average atomic mass of silicon that we
would find on the periodic table. so that
means if we took a sample of silicon
atoms and added all of their masses
together and then divided by the number
of atoms there are, we would get twenty
eight point one atomic mass units as the
average mass of all of those silicon atoms.